Guide to the Selden Rodman Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Selden Rodman papers
1935-2000
MS 871
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
5.26
The papers consist of published and unpublished writings, correspondence with a small number of acclaimed writers and artists, and handwritten journals kept between 1938 and 2000 that document the career and personal life of Selden Rodman.
Rodman, Selden, 1909-2002
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Selden Rodman, 1979-1997. Gift of the Estate of Selden Rodman, 2003. Gift of Richard Emmet Aaron, 2007.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
Arranged in three series and one addition: I. Correspondence, 1944-1984; II. Journals, 1938-2000; III. Writings, 1951-1986.
Scope and Contents
Selden Rodman was a prolific and versatile writer of poetry, plays and prose, political commentary, art criticism, Latin American and Caribbean history, biography, and travel writing - publishing a book almost every year of his adult life. The papers consist of a number of miscellaneous published and unpublished works, correspondence with acclaimed writers and artists, as well as handwritten journals kept between 1938 and 2000, which document his personal life and contain notes for many of his written publications.
Social, intellectual, and cultural historians alike will find much of benefit in Rodman's journals and correspondence. The journals document Rodman's ties to a variety of literary and artistic luminaries of the last century, including James Agee, Theodore Dreiser, W. H. Auden, Robert Frost, Jackson Pollock, Andrew Wyeth, Ernest Hemingway, Edward Hopper, Willem de Kooning, e.e. cummings, Diego Rivera, Norman Mailer, Allen Ginsberg, Octavio Paz, and Pablo Neruda and will be of interest to historians of twentieth-century art and culture. Historians of the Old Left may be interested in his evolving political consciousness and personal contacts formed while working with Common Sense, his critical and incisive accounts of the military's pervasive anti-semitism and anti-communism during World War II, and his struggles to maintain his political and artistic ideals in a politically and culturally conservative postwar context. Rodman's fascination with and travels to Haiti, specifically, and Latin America more broadly, may be of interest to historians studying the work of American intellectuals in Latin America. On a more personal side, Rodman had many romantic interests during his lifetime, and historians of gender and sexuality may be interested in, amongst other things, Rodman's frank representation of his relationships with women, sexual encounters, and extra-marital affairs. Moreover, Rodman's sustained engagement with current affairs and the remarkable span of his journals, which literally cover everything from the bombing of Pearl Harbor to that in Oklahoma City, gives readers one individual's perspective on some of the most important moments in twentieth-century American history.
Biographical / Historical
Selden Rodman was born February 19, 1909, in New York City to architect Cary Selden and wealthy socialite Nannie Van Nostrand (Marvin) Rodman. In 1927, Rodman went to Yale, where he helped found and edit the sardonic Harkness Hoot, and graduated in 1931.
After graduation and a transformative tour of Europe that included a stop in the Soviet Union, Rodman and traveling companion Alfred Bingham founded Common Sense (1932-1946), a "magazine of social protest," which boasted contributing editors like John Dewey, Upton Sinclair, Roger Baldwin, Lewis Mumford, and Max Eastman. The magazine posed a radical challenge to the politics of the New Deal, "attempting to find a place independent of both old liberalism and the newly fashionable intellectual Marxism," according to Bingham. In The Politics of Upheaval, Arthur M. Schlesinger, Jr. described the monthly political magazine as the "most lively and interesting forum of radical discussion in the country." While Bingham oversaw political and economic commentary, Rodman handled cultural matters, persuading writers like John Dos Passos, Theodore Dreiser, and W. H. Auden to contribute to the magazine. Rodman continued his work with Common Sense until enlisting in 1943, serving first in an automatic weapons battalion and later as master sergeant in the foreign nationalities section of the Office of Strategic Services.
During the war, Rodman made a trip to Haiti as an intelligence officer in 1944, when his play The Revolutionists was produced by the Haitian government. The play was such a diplomatic success that shortly after the war the Bureau of Inter-American Affairs sponsored a second trip to Haiti, where he became co-director for the Haitian Centre d'Art (1949-1951). In this position, he directed and decorated the Episcopal Cathedral of St. Trinité and initiated the famous mural painting movement in Haiti. During his tenure, Haitian folk art and famous outsider artists, like Hector Hyppolite, achieved international renown.
While posted in Washington D.C. during the war, Rodman made his entree into the world of contemporary American art, meeting influential art critic Clement Greenberg, Peggy Guggenheim, and Sam Rosenberg. By the 1950s, Rodman had become president of the Haitian Art Center in New York City and was quickly incorporated into both American art and literary circles—now internationally acclaimed with the ascendancy of American abstract expressionism and Beat poetry. Rodman interviewed many of these emerging artists and poets, including Jackson Pollock, Willem de Kooning, Allen Ginsberg, Franz Kline, and Mark Rothko for numerous publications including Conversations with Artists (1957) and Tongues of Fallen Angels (1972). Rodman also wrote a humanist's critique of these same abstract expressionists in his book The Insiders (1960), which denounced the artistic movement as void of content and championed instead figural artists like Edward Hopper, Andrew Wyeth, Ben Shawn, and Mark Tobey as the truly great contemporary American artists.
By 1960, Rodman had turned his attention to Latin America, returning first to Haiti and then traveling throughout Central and South America for the next fifteen years to publish travel guides and books on both the modern and folk arts of Latin America. While maintaining his permanent residence in Oakland, New Jersey, Rodman traveled to Mexico, Guatemala, the Dominican Republic, throughout the Caribbean, Chile, Peru, Colombia, Bolivia, Brazil, and Ecuador, where he befriended famous writers and artists, such as Diego Rivera, Octavio Paz, and Pablo Neruda. Following this tour, Rodman settled part-time in Haiti until 1992, writing plays and histories of Haitian art, expanding his private art collection, and coordinating exhibitions of Haitian art in Haiti and in the United States. In so doing, Rodman became a leading expert on Haitian art and culture.
During his lifetime, Rodman had many romantic interests, marrying Eunice Clark in 1933, Hilda Clausen in 1938, writer Maia Wojciechowska in 1950, and journalist, poet, and playwright Carole Cleaver in1962. He had one daughter with Maia, Oriana ("Beebe"), and two children with Carole, daughter Carla Pamela and son Van Nostrand.
Rodman spent his remaining years with his fourth wife Carole in Oakland, New Jersey. Having already written over forty books, plays, and exhibition catalogs in his lifetime, Rodman published his final book, Geniuses & Other Eccentrics, in 1997—a fitting recollection of his many celebrated friends. Selden Rodman died November 2, 2002.
Art; Haiti; Diaries; Baskin, Leonard, 1922-2000; Ginsberg, Allen, 1926-1997; Hemingway, Ernest, 1899-1961; Neruda, Pablo, 1904-1973; Paz, Octavio, 1914-1998; Rodman, Selden, 1909-2002; Wyeth, Andrew, 1917-2009
- Correspondence, 1944-1984, Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Arranged alphabetically, the series includes correspondence with and/or other materials about important literary and artistic figures, including Ernest Hemingway and Andrew Wyeth. These letters and notes range from standard business transactions to heated exchanges with artist and critic Leonard Baskin.
  - Baskin, Leonard
    - Correspondence, 1952-1962, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Works by Leonard Baskin, 1957-1967, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Printed material about Leonard Baskin, 1960-1964, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Diamond, Lois, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Ginsberg, Allen
    - Correspondence, 1960-1973 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Incomplete manuscript about Allen Ginsberg by Selden Rodman, 1973? (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Ginsberg, Louis
    - Correspondence, 1961-1969 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Works by Louis Ginsberg, 1958-1968, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence about the Ginsbergs, 1961, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Printed material about the Ginsbergs, 1961-1969, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Hemingway, Mary and Ernest
    - Correspondence, 1951-1973 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence about Ernest Hemingway, 1955-1962, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Love poems to Mary Welsh Hemingway by Ernest Hemingway, 1944, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Printed material about Hemingway, 1952-1972 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Neruda, Pablo
    - Correspondence, 1966-1973, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Letter about Pablo Neruda, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Printed material about Pablo Neruda, 1966-1969, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Paz, Octavio
    - Correspondence, 1959-1982, undated (Box 1A, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence about Octavio Paz, 1972, undated (Box 1A, Folder 2)
    - Printed material about Octavio Paz, 1972-1984, undated (Box 1A, Folder 3)
    - Manuscript entitled "Octavio Paz" by Selden Rodman, 1973 (Box 1A, Folder 4)
  - Wyeth, Andrew
    - Correspondence, 1956, undated (Box 1A, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence about Andrew Wyeth from David Rockefeller, 1960 (Box 1A, Folder 6)
    - Incomplete manuscript about Andrew Wyeth, undated (Box 1A, Folder 7)
    - Printed matter about Andrew Wyeth, 1963-1973, undated (Box 1A, Folder 8)
- Journals, 1938-2000, Series II
  Selden Rodman kept detailed handwritten journals for most of his adult life and the series includes journals dating from 1938-1945 and 1956-2000. In these diaries, Rodman includes notes related to his numerous book projects and creative endeavors, commentary on current events and popular culture, frank accounts of his personal relationships, and records of his travels throughout Central and South America, Europe, and the United States. The journals are organized chronologically and many are listed using Rodman's own titles, which are included in quotations. The inventory also provides brief annotations of each journal.
  While his journals often contain many or all of these elements, they can be roughly divided into four periods. Journals dating from 1938-1945 document Rodman's political stances developed during his tenure at Common Sense, the mounting tensions leading up to the war, and his experiences in service during World War II. By the 1950s, Rodman's interests had turned to contemporary art and architecture, and journals kept between 1956 and 1960 record both his evolving humanistic aesthetic philosophy and numerous conversations with important twentieth-century Mexican and American artists. Between 1960 and 1975, Rodman traveled extensively throughout Central and South America, documenting in his journals the cultural values, political climate, economic conditions, and artistic achievements of the places he visited - much of which he used in later published travel books and art criticism. Rodman had significant ties to Haiti throughout his life, and between 1976 and 1993 Rodman lived part-time in Haiti, writing several plays and advocating internationally for the country's popular artists. Journals from this period, however, deal more consistently with his troubled family life and personal affairs. The last set of journals from 1994 to 2000, kept while living back at his permanent residence in Oakland, New Jersey, are more difficult to define topically, but demonstrate a sustained engagement with contemporary politics and popular culture and poignantly reveal a growing sense of mortality.
  - 1938 - 1943; HAITI, Frost, Spender, Faulkner [political philosophy as developed in Common Sense; Conversations with modern American poets (James Agee, W. H. Auden, Theodore Dreiser, Christopher Isherwood, etc.); Notes for The Airmen (1941); documents anxieties in years leading up to WWII and early years in Army; first trip to South America; marriage to Hilda Clausen; ends with interviews from 1948-1951 with Robert Frost, Ezra Pound, William Faulkner, and Ernest Hemingway] (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - "1943-45: WAR" [Records experiences in the war, including commentary on culture of armed officers; notes for and critical reception of The Revolutionists (1942); life in Washington D.C. working with Office of Strategic Services; early contact with American art scene and critics (Peggy Guggenheim, Sam Rosenberg, Clement Greenberg)] (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - "1956: ARTISTS; West Coast", "May-Oct 56; ARTISTS": [interviews with American artists and architects such as Jackson Pollock, Frank Lloyd Wright, Mark Rothko, Ad Reinhardt and Edward Hopper for Conversations with Artists (1957); relationship w/ 3rd wife, Maia Wojciechowska] (Box 2, Folder 3 - 4)
  - "MEX: 1956-1957," "1957: MEX Feb.-Apr.," and "MEX II: Yucatan, Jan '57" [travel diaries with notes used for Mexican Journal: The Conquerers Conquered (1958); includes interviews w/ Diego Rivera] (Box 2, Folder 5 - 6)
  - "ARTISTS 1959 Jan-August": [notes for The Insiders (1960), a critique of abstract expressionism and treatise on humanism in art] (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - "1959 Aug-Dec 31; HAITI; Artists, EE Cum": [notes on travels across country and Haiti with daughter, Oriana ("Beebe")] (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - "1960 Jan-Dec": [budding relationship with eventual fourth wife, Carole Cleaver. Conversations with Norman Mailer, Arthur Schlesinger, and Bruce Neuman] (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - 1960 (Sep) - 1961 (May), "1961 June-Oct" [return to poetry; writes The Heart of Beethoven (1962); notes on pressures to conform in Cold War context; reflections on his relationship w/ women] (Box 3, Folder 10 - 11)
  - "Jan-Sept 1961-2 HAITI" [on romantic relationships, art, and travels through Haiti] (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - "1962 Apr-July; MEXICO Interioristas": [travels in Mexico] (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - "1962 July-Nov.": [life at home in Oakland, New Jersey] (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - "MEX-GUAT 1963-1964 [embarks on tour of Central America, traveling to Mexico and Guatemala with wife Carole and infant daughter Carla. Includes more interviews with artists, commentary on tourist industry, and notes for The Guatemala Traveler (1967)] (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - "DOMINCAN REPUBLIC, 1963 Jan-Apr": [travel diary concerned especially with political instability in the aftermath of dictator Rafael Trujillo's assassination] (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - "64 MEX Feb-Jun": [conversations with Mexican artists and scholars] (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - "1964 July-Dec": [at home in Oakland, New Jersey.; meets Allen Ginsberg and introduced to "The Metro," a Beat poetry collective] (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - "Guatemala, Dec 64-Apr 65": [documents travels throughout Central America, including Guatemala, Haiti, the Dominican Republic, El Salvador, Nicaragua, Costa Rica, and Panama, for The Road to Panama (1966)] (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - "1965 June 2-Oct 22; Rev. in D.R.": [travel diary with continued interest in the political reconstruction of the Dominican Republic] (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - "PERU: Dec 65-Apr 66": [records travels in Peru, with emphasis on the visual arts, the status of indigenous peoples and culture, and the political and economic climate for The Peru Traveler (1967). Includes clippings and ephemera] (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - "1966 May-Nov; D.R., HAITI": [travels to Central American, returning to the Dominican Republic and Haiti] (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - "The Caribbean"; "Appendix to Caribbean Journal": [travels to twenty-five islands in the Caribbean from 1966-1967, documenting culture, racial tensions, economic conditions, and political climate. Later publishes The Caribbean (1968)] (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - "MEXICO": [documents trip to Mexico in 1968 for The Mexico Traveler (1969)] (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - "CHILE.. .", Vol. I, II: [chronicles 1969 cultural tour throughout South America and conversations with many important South American literary figures, including Pablo Neruda, for South America of the Poets (1970)] (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - 1970 (Colombia) [records travels in and cultural/political life of Colombia for The Colombian Traveler (1971)] (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - "1970 Peru, Chile, Bolivia; Ginsberg, Kunitz, Pippin": [more thoughts on travels through South America as well as early notes for Horace Pippin (1972), co-authored by wife Carole Cleaver] (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - "COLOMBIA.. ." [1971 travel diary from tour of South America; includes clippings and ephemera] (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - "HAITI, BRAZIL; Mailer, Ginsberg, Walcott": [travel diary (Oct 1971- Mar 1972) with notes for The Brazil Traveler (1975); includes supplemental material and ephemera] (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - 1972-1974 (Haiti) [three journals and supplement, which record experiences living in Haiti and thoughts on country's cultural, economic, and political climate; his consulting work for new Haitian art museum; includes clippings, ephemera, and other materials Vol. I and II] (Box 8, Folder 30 - 31)
  - "1975": [in Haiti and Washington D.C.; includes travel notes, more art theory, critical reception of Tongues of Fallen Angels (1974), and reflections on his relationship with wife and children] (Box 8, Folder 32)
  - 1975 Nov-Dec: [travel diary with artist interviews for Genius in the Backlands: Popular Artists of Brazil (1977)] (Box 8, Folder 33)
  - 1976 Nov-1977 Dec; 1977 Dec-1978 Jun: [self-reflective diaries written mostly while living in Haiti, with focus on troubled marriage and family life] (Box 9, Folder 34)
  - 1978 Oct-1979 Jul: [first half includes notes from trip with Carole to Germany and Austria on German culture and history; latter half describes return to Haiti and travels in France and Spain] (Box 9, Folder 35)
  - 1979 Oct-1980 Jan; 1980 Feb-Aug; 1980 Aug-1981 Jan: [more travels in Mexico, Ecuador, Peru, and Haiti, with ostensible purpose of documenting second renaissance of Haitian art and expanding personal art collection; more focus in all three on troubles with son, Van Nostrand] (Box 9, Folder 36 - 37)
  - "Renaissance II" Journals 1981 Feb-Nov; 1981 Nov-Mar 1982: [collecting art on various trips to Haiti and mounting traveling exhibition in U.S. titled "Three Generations of Haitian Art;" continued emphasis on troubled family life] (Box 10, Folder 38)
  - "Journal of Two Months of Crisis," 1982 Sep-Nov: [ongoing family tensions climax with wife Carole's attempted suicide] (Box 10, Folder 39)
  - "Renaissance II" cont'd or "Jacmel, Haiti," 1982 Dec-1983 Nov; 1983 Dec-1984 Apr; 1984 Jun-Nov; 1984 Dec-1985 Mar; 1985 Apr-Oct; 1985 Nov-1986 Apr; 1986 May-Nov; 1986 Nov-1987 Aug; 1987 Aug-Nov; 1987 Nov-1988 Aug: [ten journals from the 1980s kept while living in Jacmel, Haiti; occasional entries on politics or art, but mostly deals with personal matters, including relationship with wife and daughters, extra-marital affairs, and son's ongoing struggle with substance abuse; '85-'86 journal includes notes for autobiography, and final journal discusses controversial 1988 elections in Haiti and American intervention] (Box 10, Folder 40 - 45)
  - "Renaissance III," 1988 Aug-Dec: [from Haiti to Puerto Rico] (Box 10, Folder 46)
  - 1988 Dec-1989 Dec: [living in Puerto Rico with Carole] (Box 11, Folder 47)
  - 1989 Dec-1990 Aug; 1990 Aug-1991 Dec: [returns to Haiti; on personal matters, art, and political instability in Central America] (Box 11, Folder 48 - 49)
  - 1991 Dec-1993 Sep (Puerto Rico and Haiti): [on aging, relationships with extended family, American politics, and popular culture] (Box 11, Folder 50)
  - 1993 Sep-Dec 1994: [returns from Haiti to Oakland, New Jersey; travels to Russia] (Box 11, Folder 51)
  - 1994 Dec-1995 Dec: [living in Oakland, New Jersey, but still concerned with Haiti's economic and political status as well as current events nationally and internationally; last third dedicated primarily to dream description and interpretation] (Box 11, Folder 52)
  - 1996 Jan-Oct; 1996 Oct-1997 Aug; 1997 Sep-2000 Dec: [journals kept while living in Oakland, New Jersey with wife Carole; final trip to Port-au-Prince to buy art; more dream interpretation, entries on current affairs, and thoughts on aging] (Box 11, Folder 53 - 54)
- Writings, 1951-1986, Series III
  Arranged alphabetically by type of writing, the series includes art exhibition catalogs, an article, a book, correspondence relating to the publication of The Insiders, and numerous unpublished plays written between 1972 and 1983.
  - Art catalogs, 1979-1986 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Article--"Forty Years After: The Nazi Heartland" [published in National Review ], 1979 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Books
    - The Insiders [correspondence and printed materials], 1951-1969 (Box 12, Folder 3 - 4)
    - Tongues of Fallen Angels, 1972 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Plays and Screenplays
    - "The Black King," (unpublished screenplay) by Selden Rodman, 1977 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - "The Fool of Passion, or What Happened to Lord Byron's Marriage (1812-1816)," (unpublished play) by Selden Rodman, 1983 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - "Hustler of the Gods," (unpublished play) by Selden Rodman and Carole Cleaver, 1975 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - "The Liberator Liberated, or Bolivar's Dream," (unpublished play) by Selden Rodman, 1976 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - "The Phantom Express" (unpublished musical) by Maia Wojciechowska and Selden Rodman, 1982 (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - "Saint of the Revolution" (unpublished play) by Selden Rodman, 1978 (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - "Trazom!," (unpublished play) by Selden Rodman, 1985 (Box 13, Folder 12)
- Additional Material, 1935-1948, undated; Accession 2007-M-057
  Correspondence between Hilda Clausen and Selden Rodman.
  - Correspondence, 1935-1948, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)